# Karan Samel

## ksamel@gatech.edu (925) 400-3027 https://karans.github.io/

My current research revolves around joining deep learning with symbolic reasoning to reduce the number of labels required. I am also interested in structured prediction methods, and ML in the domain of healthcare and drug discovery applications.

**EDUCATION** 

## Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

August 2019 - Present

Ph.D. in Machine Learning - Advisor: Prof. Le Song

## Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

August 2014 - May 2017

B.S in Computer Science, Applied Statistics - Graduated with Highest Distinction

**EXPERIENCE** 

#### Georgia Institute of Technology: Research Assistant

August 2019 - Present

 Researching incorporating structure into multi-modal tasks, such as visual question answering, to reduce label and computation complexities. This is done through primarily neuro-symbolic methods.

#### IBM Research AI: Research Intern

June 2020 - August 2020

• Developed methods for complex time series events using deep learning and logical reasoning, primarily focusing on video data. Worked within the continuous AI team.

#### **Astound: Data Scientist**

July 2017 – June 2019

- Researched and engineered human-in-the-loop machine learning systems to improve data quality.
  Method developed is optimized to reduce human annotator feedback while maximizing the performance of deep learning models. Resulting paper accepted at KDD'18.
- Developed transfer learning methods to improve a deep learning model performance given limited data

### Undergraduate Researcher: Advertisement Real Time Bidding Predictions August 2015 – May 2017

- Tested various deep learning architectures to predict customer clicks on the iPinYou advertisement dataset. Achieved high prediction scores even with sparse positive click data.
- Utilized an external GPU setup to speed up convolutional network training by a factor of 80.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

DePe: Differentiable End-to-end Program Executor for Sample and Computationally Efficient VQA

**Karan Samel**, Zelin Zhao, Kuan Wang, Robin Luo, Binghong Chen, Le Song Under review at the *International Conference of Learning Representations (ICLR) 2021* 

Abductive Visual Question Answering for Label Efficient Learning **Karan Samel**, Binghong Chen, Le Song Preprint 2020. [PDF]

Active Deep Learning to Tune Down the Noise in Labels

Karan Samel, Xu Miao

In Proceedings of the 24th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery & Data Mining (KDD'18). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 685-694. [PDF]

Predicting Advertisement Clicks Using Deep Networks: Interpreting Deep Learning Models **Karan Samel**, Xiao Wang, Qiang Liu In *The Journal of Purdue Undergraduate Research*: Vol. 7, Article 8. [PDF]

#### **GRANTS & AWARDS**

- Georgia Tech President's Fellowship (2019 2023)
- NSF GRFP Honorable Mention: Relational Recursive Models for Trustable Medical Diagnoses (2019)
- KDD Startup Research Award (2018)
- NSF Mentoring Through Critical Transition Points in the Mathematical Sciences: Purdue Statistics Living Learning Community (Grant No. 1246818) (2016 2017)
- Purdue Presidential Scholarship (Awarded for 2014 2018)

#### PENDING PATENTS

A Method and System for Composite Event Estimation Through Temporal Logic (IBM, filing pending) **Karan Samel**, Dharmashankar Subramanian

Framework for Building and Sharing Machine Learning Components (Astound.ai, filed 2020) Xu Miao, Masayo Iida, Zhenjie Zhang, **Karan Samel**, Adil Mohammed, Baiji He, Ankit Arya, Naghi Prasad

Active Deep Learning to Reduce Noise in Labels (Astound.ai, filed 2019) **Karan Samel**, Xu Miao, Zhenjie Zhang, Masayo Iida, Naghi Prasad